The ship operated the distance between the city of Tacloban
and the capital of Manilla in the Philippines, located on the island of Luzon
With an intermediate stop in the city of Catbalogan on the island of Samar.
This route did Doña Paz twice a week.
When the ship left the harbor it was scheduled to arrive at Manilla the clock
Four in the morning the day after.
Philippines is a country consisting of
over 7000 islands and is completely dependent on vessels or boats as a means of transport between the islands,
Which makes passenger ferries the most economical mode of transport for many locals.
According to reports it is apparently very common
that the ferries are overloaded in the Philippines.
So even if a ship such as Doña Paz can only
3 to 4 people could split on a single bed.
The ship's communication system was broken so they could not call for help if needed.
The Life Rights on board were locked up in a separate room
And if that wasn't enough, the ship was also ruled at this time
An apprentice without sufficient experience.
The captain and the rest of the officers were either at the bar or watched TV in their staff room
And on board MT Vector it wasn't much better.
They were heavily understaffed with only 13 men.
They had no training in dealing with crisis situations, inadequate navigation equipment and that
In its most recent inspection of the Philippine Coast Guard was discovered
That an MT Vector had an error on the steering.
The radio license had expired 1.5 years ago and they missed
also an inspection certificate.
which led to an immediate and powerful explosion.
The explosion was so violent that
It immediately settled both vessels on fire.
The passengers had nowhere to go.
The oil had leaked into the sea, as well as the water around.
Both vessels were in flames.
No lifeboats could be hoisted down because of it.
The fire spread rapidly on deck and looked into cabins
And the social spaces that packed with people.